Guide to the Roe Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Series VII, Henry Roe Cloud Papers, is located in Boxes 67-72 of the Roe Family Papers and contains. correspondence and other material relating to Henry Roe Cloud. Most of the correspondence is with Walter Clark Roe and Mary Wickham Roe and dates from Cloud's student years, 1907-1914. These letters are almost entirely personal. Subjects discussed include Cloud's adjustment to Yale, his student life and activities, career choices, and conditions among American Indians, particularly within his own tribe. Correspondence with Mary Wickham Roe traces the relationship between the missionary and her adopted son, who apparently shared many of her ideas and concerns.
After 1914, the amount of correspondence diminishes sharply. While Mary Wickham Roe continues to be the major correspondent, most letters are now business-like in tone and concern the founding and funding of Roe Indian Institute. There are also letters from Elizabeth Bender Cloud to "Mother Roe", containing family news. Cousin Elizabeth Merwin Page Harris becomes a regular correspondent during the 1930's and 1940's. These letters discuss her mother's failing health, Cloud's own heart condition, family concerns, and her historical novels.
There is, however, almost no documentation of Cloud's professional life. Several letters to G. Elmer E. Lindquist and J. Leighton Read concern Indian education, and in a 1945 letter to Bee, Henry comments unfavorably on Indian Affairs Commissioner John Collier. In addition to correspondence, the series also contains newspaper clippings, drafts of articles and speeches, and Cloud's 1916 autobiographical pamphlet, "From Wigwam to Pulpit". Two copies of the 1928 Meriam Report, co-authored by Cloud, can be found in Series XI, Box 137, and an additional folder of material can be found in Box 164 of the Roe Addition.
Series VIII, Missionary Correspondence, is housed in Boxes 73-82 of the Roe Family Papers and contains correspondence connected with the missionary careers of Walter Clark Roe and Mary Wickham Roe. From 1897 until approximately 1920, most of the correspondence is concerned with the Indian missions of the Reformed Church in America, and covers a wide variety of subjects. Topics include the operation of the missions, social conditions and educational needs of reservation Indians, Indian attachment to tribal customs, and missionary dissatisfaction with policies of the Bureau of Indian Affairs.
Information on the routine operations of the missions, especially of Colony, and on the Reformed Church's mission efforts in general, can be found in the letters of officials of the Women's Board of Domestic Missions. Correspondents include Board Presidents Emily Bussing (1893-1925) and Elsie Maynard (1926-1928); Corresponding Secretaries Edith Allen (1904-1926) and Ruth Rule (1927-1932); Office Secretary Helen Voorhees (1911-1930); and Chairmen of the Committee on Indian Work Louise Runk (1896-1921) and Ada Quinley Knox (1922-1929). Mary Wickham Roe's sister Lillie was Field Secretary from 1903-1913. Her correspondence is found in Series I, Family Correspondence, and in the Page Family Papers. Correspondence with Commissioners of Indian Affairs Francis Leupp, C.H. Larrabee, R.S. Valentine, R.M. Preston, and Cato Sells documents missionary reactions to governmental policies concerning Indians, as do letters of various agency superintendents with jurisdiction over specific missions.
Much of the above material relates to the mission at Colony, the earliest and most important of the Reformed Church foundations. Correspondents of the Roes from Colony include Frank Hall Wright (at Colony 1894-1897), Henry A. Vruwink (1913-1922), John H. Baxter (1923-1926), Richard H. Harper (1927-1929), Peter Van Es (1930-1932), and mission assistants Mary Jensen and Johanna Meengs. The letters of benefactor Kate Olcott contain many financial details about the mission. Colony has a significant number of Indian correspondents, including Paul and Edna Goodbear, William Ohlerking, John Fletcher, Frank Hamilton, Ella Butts, Richard Birdhead, Wautan Wauzitza, Two Crows, and John Ottipoby. Their letters shed much light on the daily lives of Oklahoma Indians in the early twentieth century, as well as revealing a variety of attitudes toward white culture and tribal customs. There is also correspondence with local agency superintendents Walter Dickens and John H. Seger, usually reflecting missionary disapproval of government policies. Additional information concerning Colony can be found in the letters of Reese Kincaide, director of Mohonk Lodge, a mission-sponsored Indian crafts co-operative; and in the post-1916 letters of G.A. Watermulder, superintendent of missions for the Reformed Church.
The other Reformed Church missions are also well-represented in this series. The Comanche-Lawton preaching station is discussed by several missionaries, including Leonard and Maud Legters, J. Leighton Read, and Robert Chaat. The letters of J. Denton Simms provide information on the impoverished and still tribal Jicarilla Apaches served by Dulce Mission. Walter Clark Roe's Ft. Sill correspondents include missionaries Hendrina Hospers, Clover Mahan, and Mary MacMillan. The Mescalero correspondence is more extensive, and contains details of the missionaries' fight to protect the reservation from National Park status. Correspondents include E.M. Fincher (at Mescalero 1908-1913), Richard H. Harper (1913-1915), James Dykema (1916-1920), N.E. and Marjorie Overman (1920-1931), John L. Mixon (1931-1933), and Peter Van Es (1933). Finally, the correspondence from Winnebago Mission contains detailed discussions of reservation policies and of the rise of the peyote cult. Correspondents include missionaries G.A. Watermulder and Anna Berkenpas, Agency Superintendent Albert H. Kneale, and Indians Louisa Johnson Bear, Eva DuPuis Gover, and Lucy Hunter.
Other correspondents concerned with North American missions and Indian welfare are G. Elmer E. Lindquist, first principal of the Roe Indian Institute and later Chairman of the Y.M.C.A. Committee on Indian Work; Robert D. Hall of the Rosebud Indian Mission; and S.M. Brosius of the Indian Rights Association.
Many of these correspondents continue writing through the 1920's and, in some cases, the 1930's. The focus of the collection, however, changes in the early 1920's. There is more generalized discussion of Indian welfare and of governmental policies toward the Indians. The letters of Mary Wickham Roe are particularly critical of what she perceived as the Bureau of Indian Affairs' tolerance of tribalism and immorality, especially under the controversial direction of John Collier. In addition, the missionaries in the field begin to find the decisions of the Women's Board confusing and uninformed about the real needs of the Indians. The collection documents these changes in Board policy, which led to the closing of Colony mission and the partial abandonment of Dulce in 1932.
Beginning in the 1920's, the correspondence also reflects Mary Wickham Roe's increased interest in Protestant evangelization efforts among the Indians of Latin America. Correspondents include missionaries Dorothy and Dudley Peck, Paul Burgess, R. Esther Smith, Georgia Robertson, Harry Strachan, Lacy Simms, and Leonard Legters, as well as exchange students Jose Chicol and Anhel Castro. Topics include the status of Indians in Latin America, the lack of basic literacy in Mexico and Guatamala, and the missionaries' dislike of native Roman Catholic practices. Many other subjects are discussed in the correspondence. Researchers can find, for example, correspondence on land allotment, farming practices, the ration system, Indian fairs, boarding-school education, and tribal customs. In general, the series provides insight into the views of missionaries on reservation life and tribal activities.
Boxes 83-102 contain Series IX, Missionary Papers, which consists of a variety of materials relating to Indians and to mission work among them. The series has been divided into four sections: North American Missions of the Reformed Church in America; Other Missions to Indians of North America; Indians of North America; and Missions to the Indians of Latin America.
Section one, North American Missions of the Reformed Church in America, fills Boxes 83-87. It begins with material on the Women's Board of Domestic Missions, including several annual reports, a 1932 history of the Board's religious work, and several folders of pamphlets, newspaper clippings, obituaries, and speech notes. The remainder of the section is arranged alphabetically by name of mission. All of the missions connected with the Roes' work are represented. Colony material includes financial accounts, records of camp-meetings and conferences, several folders of Indian testimonials, circular letters detailing mission activities 1899-1930, newspaper clippings, and pamphlets on life at the mission, some of which were written by the Roes. Circular letters, clippings, and mission pamphlets are also available for Comanche-Lawton and Dulce-Jicarilla Missions. Material on Ft. Sill-Apache Mission includes papers on prisoner relief for the Geronimo band. There is one folder of papers relating to the reservation rights campaign at Mescalero Mission. The material on Winnebago Mission includes Indian testimonials and copies of the 1913 "Monthly Recorder". (See also Box 164 of the Roe Addition.)
Section two, Other Missions, is contained in Boxes 87-88 of the Roe Family Papers. It consists almost entirely of pamphlets and leaflets on various Protestant missions to Indians, such as those operated by the Presbyterian Church in the U.S. and the Methodist Episcopal Church.
Section three, Indians of North America, is housed in Boxes 88-97 and is devoted to non-mission papers. There is considerable material on the Bureau of Indian Affairs, including addresses, several annual reports, informational bulletins, and an extensive run of Indians at Work, a Bureau publication edited by John Collier. Four folders of magazine and newspaper clippings contain articles detailing the missionary view of Bureau policies, including one on John Collier (Box 94, folder 1639). A history of the Reformed Church's mission work can be found in the September and December, 1940 issues of The Chronicles of Oklahoma. Account books, catalogs, and newspaper articles relating to Mohonk Lodge, an Indian crafts co-operative, have been placed in this section. In addition, the collection contains smaller amounts of material on many organizations and topics, including the American Indian Institute, the Indian Rights Association, the early Lake Mohonk Conferences on the Indian, writings by and obituaries of John H. Seger, and a folder of material on the peyote cult.
Section four, Missions to the Indians of Latin America, fills Boxes 98-102 and consists mostly of pamphlets, circular letters, and newspaper and magazine clippings which describe Protestant missionary activities. The section contains materials on the Reformed Church's mission in Chiapas, Mexico; the evangelical Committee on Co-Operation in Latin America; and the Chiquimula mission to the Cakchikel Indians in Guatamala. There are also several folders of general-interest newspaper and magazine clippings.
Series X, Missionary Photographs, is located in Boxes 103-15 and has been divided into three sections: Missions of the Reformed Church in America, Indians of North America, and Latin America. All photographs which could be identified as pertaining to a specific mission have been placed in the first section. These include views, portraits of Indians and missionaries, and group shots. There are several albums which date from the earliest years of Colony and Ft. Sill. Section two, Indians of North America, contains many interesting studio portraits (ca. 1900-1915) which provide details of contemporary costume. One such photograph shows a young woman in full traditional dress carrying an ivory-handled parasol. There are also group portraits, portraits of several peyote cult leaders, and views. The third section, Latin America, consists of photographs and postcards from Mary Wickham Roe's trip to Central and South America. Box 112 contains glass negatives.
Boxes 113-115 contain Oversize family papers and photographs. These include Civil War records of Alfred Cox Roe, a genealogical chart kept by Joseph Wickham Roe, and portraits of several members of the Roe family. The Oversized Mission photographs include early views of Colony Mission and Seger School.
Boxes 116-155 house Series XI, Indian Book Collection. The collection belonged to Walter Clark and Mary Wickham Roe, and it contains books on many aspects of Indian life and culture in both North America and Latin America. Many of the books on Latin America are accounts of Protestant evangelization activity. Several works in the collection were written by friends and correspondents of the Roes, including Albert H. Kneale's Indian Agent, G. Elmer E. Lindquist's The Jesus Road and the Red Man, and John H. Seger's Early Days Among the Cheyenne and Arapaho Indians.
The Addition to the Roe Family appers is located in Boxes 156-164 and has been divided into six series. Series I, Family Correspondence, contains correspondence of Joseph Wickham Roe. It consists primarily of 1902 courtship letters written by his first wife, Nellie Allen Roe, and letters written by Joseph to his cousin, Miranda B. Merwin. Estate papers and memorabilia of Joseph Wickham Roe are located in Series II together with an unpublished manuscript by his father Alfred Cox Roe. Printed Works, Series V, includes a copy of Mary Abigail Roe's E.P. Roe: Reminiscences of His Life. There are two small albums of family pictures and several portraits in Series VI, Family Photographs. Also included is a folder of Henry Roe Cloud Papers and the Addition concludes with three folders of Missionary Papers. These contain a fifty year history of the Indian work of the Women's Board of Domestic Missions, notes on camp-meetings in the hand of Elizabeth Page Harris, and a "Pageant of Indian History at Colony" also by Elizabeth Page Harris.
Biographical / Historical
Alfred Cox Roe And Emma Wickham Roe
Alfred Cox Roe was born on April 7, 1823. The eldest son of Peter Elting and Susan Williams Roe, he grew up in Cornwall on the Hudson, New York, and graduated from New York University in 1843. The following year he established the Cornwall English and Classical School in the Canterbury district of Cornwall, New York, at which he taught for almost two decades. Ordained by the Presbyterian Church in 1863, Roe was appointed chaplain to the 83rd Regiment of New York Volunteers. This unit was destroyed at the Battle of Weldon Railroad in August 1864 and Roe was re-commissioned in the 104th Regiment, in which he served until his discharge in July 1865. He was Eastern Secretary of the American Christian Commission in New York City 1866-1869. In 1870-1871 he was pastor of a Presbyterian church in Lowell, Massachusetts. He then returned to New York state, serving Presbyterian congregations in Geneva 1871-1873, Galen 1873-1874, and Clyde 1875-1876. He moved to Cornwall on the Hudson in 1877, and, there founded the Cornwall Collegiate Institute for Young Ladies. The school failed in 1882, and he returned to New York City, where he opened the Berkeley Institute in Brooklyn in 1883, followed in 1888 by the New York Collegiate Institute of Harlem. Roe retired in 1895. He and his wife then joined their daughter and son-in-law, Mary Wickham and Walter Clark Roe, in Texas, and moved with them to Colony, Oklahoma in 1897. Alfred Cox Roe and his wife returned East in 1901, and settled at the Wickham home in Manchester, Vermont, where he died in September of that year.
Alfred Cox Roe married Caroline Powell Childs (-1859) in 1847. Three children survived to adulthood: Frank Childs Roe (1850-1889), Susan Williams Roe (1852-1873), and Caroline Powell Roe Landon (1859-1897). In October, 1860, Roe married Emma Wickham (1832-1901). Surviving children were Elizabeth Merwin Roe Page (1861-1943), Mary Wickham Roe (1863-1941), and Joseph Wickham Roe (1871-1960).
Emma Wickham Roe was born in New Haven, Connecticut on October 23, 1832. She was the only child of Joseph Dresser Wickham and Amy Porter Wickham, who died shortly after Emma's birth. She attended York Square Academy in New Haven in 1845-1846, and also attended Burr and Burton Seminary, of which her father was principal, in Manchester, Vermont. During 1854-1855 she taught French and music at Oxford Academy, where her step-mother, Elizabeth Merwin Wickham, had been preceptress. Emma Wickham married Alfred Cox Roe in 1860, and accompanied him in his many career changes. After her husband's death, she remained in Manchester until her death in December 1906.
* * * * *
Mary Abigail Roe
Mary Abigail Roe, youngest sister of Alfred Cox Roe, was born in Cornwall on the Hudson in 1839, and attended Burr and Burton Seminary in Manchester. Never married, she kept house for her father until his death in 1877. She then became a teacher of natural history, first at Cornwall Collegiate Institute and then at Berkeley Institute, both founded by Alfred Cox Roe. During the late 1880's she taught at Los Angeles College, and several years later became an instructor at the Lady Jane Gray Academy in Binghamton, New York. She published at least three novels, Free, Yet Forging Their Own Chains; Left in the Wilderness; and A Long Search, and wrote Reminiscences of E.P. Roe after the sudden death of her novelist brother. Mary Abigail Roe retired to Manchester around 1900 and later moved to Watertown, New York, where she died in 1920.
* * * * *
Walter Clark Roe and Mary Wickham Roe
Walter Clark Roe was born in 1859, the second son of James Gilbert and Caroline Clark Roe. He attended Sigler's Institute in Newburgh, New York and graduated from Williams College in 1881. He taught at the Brooklyn Polytechnic Institute and in 1884 joined the faculty of the Hill School in Pennsylvania, where he remained until stricken with tuberculosis in 1889. With his wife Mary Wickham Roe, he moved to Ft. Worth, Texas and studied for the ministry while convalescing. Ordained by the Southern Presbyterian Church in 1892, he served four mission stations in the Ft. Worth area before being called to a Dallas church. While there, Roe became interested in the Indian missionary work of the Reverend Frank Hall Wright and in 1897 he succeeded Wright as head of the mission of the Reformed Church in America at Colony, Oklahoma. In 1908 he was named Superintendent of Indian Missions for that church. Roe also took up the cause of Geronimo's Apache band, then prisoners of war at Ft. Sill, and in 1912 journeyed to Washington, D.C. on their behalf. Already suffering from Addison's Disease, he sailed for the Bahamas in hopes of recovery and died in Nassau on March 12, 1913.
Walter Clark Roe married Mary Wickham Roe, his first cousin, in 1887. The couple had no surviving children. Both Roe and his wife always referred to Henry Roe Cloud as their adopted son, and he incorporated their name into his in 1908.
Mary Wickham Roe, daughter of Alfred Cox and Emma Wickham Roe, was born in 1863 and educated at her father's schools. In 1883 she became a teacher at the New York Normal School, now Hunter College, and in 1885 joined her cousin, Walter Clark Roe, at the Hill School; they were married two years later. Following their 1889 move to Texas, Mary taught at the Ft. Worth High School. She worked closely with her husband at the Colony Mission and after his death continued to serve the Reformed Church as a missionary and advisor until 1924, living at Colony and making many lecture tours for the Women's Board of Domestic Missions. In the 1920's, she became interested in Protestant missionary efforts among Latin American Indians. She visited several of these missions and was a delegate to the 1925 Pan-American Mission Conference in Montevideo, Uruguay. She left Colony in 1931 and settled in Claremont, California. Despite some ill-health, she remained interested in mission work and was attending a mission conference in New Mexico when she was killed in an automobile accident on June 17, 1941.
* * * * *
Joseph Wickham Roe
Joseph Wickham Roe, born in 1871, was the youngest child of Alfred Cox and Emma Wickham Roe. He prepared for college at Burr and Burton Seminary and at the Hill School, and graduated from Yale's Sheffield Scientific School in 1895. Following graduation, he worked for several manufacturing companies, but returned to Yale in 1906, received the M.E. in 1907, and taught mechanical engineering and machine design at Sheffield Scientific School until 1917. In that year, he was commissioned a major in the Aviation Section, Signal Reserve Corps of the Army. After the war, he worked briefly in private industry, returning to teaching in 1921 as professor and chairman of the Department of Industrial Engineering at New York University, from which he retired in 1937. He was a consultant for the Navy during World War II. Joseph Wickham Roe was the author of numerous articles and several books on engineering and management. He spent his retirement years at Southport, Connecticut, where he died in 1960.
He married Nellie Allen of Dallas in November, 1902; she died in January, 1903. In 1915, he married Mrs. Mary Sherwood Lambertson of Southport, who died in 1960. The couple had no children, but Mrs. Lambertson had one daughter, Elizabeth L. Pratt, by her first husband.
* * * * *
Henry Roe Cloud
Henry Roe Cloud was born on December 28, 1886 in Winnebago, Nebraska, the son of Winnebago parents who died when he was young. Cloud attended an Indian school in Nebraska, prepared for college at Mt. Hermon, and entered Yale in 1906. In his freshman year he was befriended by Walter Clark and Mary Wickham Roe and soon after began using the name of these adoptive parents. He received his A.B. in 1910, becoming the first Indian to graduate from Yale. In 1913 he earned his B.D. from Auburn Theological Seminary and was ordained in the Presbyterian Church. After taking his M.A. at Yale in 1915, he founded the Roe Indian Institute (later the American Indian Institute) in Wichita, Kansas and served as its superintendent for fifteen years. Roe Cloud was co-author of the 1928 Meriam Report on Indian administration and in 1931 he was named special regional representative of the Office of Indian Affairs. He was appointed superintendent of Haskell Institute in Wichita, Kansas in 1933, the first full-blooded Indian to hold that position. Cloud left the Institute in 1936 to become assistant supervisor of Indian education-at-large in the Office of Indian Affairs. His further posts were superintendent of the Umatilla Indian Agency in Pendleton, Oregon and regional representative of the Grande Ronde and Siletz Indian Agency. Cloud was active in the Society of American Indians and at one time served as the editor of the Indian Outlook.
Henry Roe Cloud married Elizabeth Georgian Bender in 1916. A Chippewa and a graduate of Hampton Institute, Elizabeth Bender Cloud served as Boy's Matron and Financial Executive at the American Indian Institute for almost twenty years. In 1951 she was named Oregon Mother of the Year. The couple had four surviving children: Elizabeth Marion (b. 1917), Anne Woisha (b. 1918), Lillian Alberta (b. 1920), and Ramona Clark (b. 1922).
For charts outlining the genealogical relations of the Roe, Page, Porter, Sherwood, and Wickham families, please consult the Genealogical Charts.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.